A Guide to the Papers of James Bertram Haugh 1975-1978
Special Collections and University Archives, Patricia W. and J. Douglas Perry Library, Old Dominion University
Special Collections and University Archives, Patricia W. and J. Douglas Perry Library, Old Dominion University
Papers of James Bertram Haugh 1975-1978
Special Collections and University Archives, Patricia W. and J. Douglas Perry Libraryy, Old Dominion University
MG 70
6 Hollinger Document Cases and 2 oversize boxes.
Administrative Information
Access
Open to researchers without restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Gift of James Bertram Haugh, January 1988.
Biographical/Historical Information
James Bertram Haugh grew up on a working class dairy farm in Indiana. In high school, he was elected president of the Future Farmers of America and of his senior class. Upon graduation, he enrolled at Carroll College in Waukesha, Wisconsin. After holding several odd labor jobs, he knew that he wanted more in life. This inspired him to achieve better academically. He attempted seminary twice, drove a Chicago Transit Authority bus for a year, and worked for I.B.M. for 6 1/2 years. Later, he began a degree in Urban Studies at Loyola, and worked toward certification in secondary education in 1970. In 1973, James Haugh began teaching in the Sociology department of Old Dominion University, and continued his studies there. At this time, he became increasingly interested in economic, community, political, and labor organization, migrant labor, social change from the standpoint of the powerless, and hunger and malnutrition. In 1974, he became involved in a hunger organization called C.R.O.P. at a conference on hunger in Richmond. Haugh was eventually asked to serve as executive director of the organization.
It was these experiences, the connections he made through them, and his desire to learn what is needed to effect positive social change that led him to do his dissertation on power and influence in the Public Voluntary Not for Profit Sector. This study was carried out largely through a series of interviews with notable public figures in a place called "Colonial City" in 1977 and 1978. "Colonial City" is actually Norfolk, Virginia, and the people interviewed are given aliases in his study. Haugh posed these people with questions about the qualities possessed by effective leaders, what it is to be a "Virginian", how things get done, and what could make or break a project in the community. The results of his study are written into a book called Power and Influence in a Colonial City. His dissertation complete, James Bertram Haugh received his Ph.D. in Sociology from the University of Akron, Ohio, in the fall of 1978.
Scope and Content Information
The papers of James Bertram Haugh relate mainly to his course work at the University of Akron in 1977 and 1978. The majority of this collection encompasses his dissertation. Included are interviews with prominent Norfolk citizens in 1977-78, newspaper articles about these people, resource articles for the study, and several rough drafts of the chapters of the dissertation. Also contained in this collection are other papers and course work by Haugh, and information on the Assembly on the Dimensions of Hunger and Malnutrition of which Haugh was a part.
Organization
The collection is broken down into the following series: I: Study of the Public Voluntary Not For Profit Sector of Colonial City; II: Other Papers and Course Work by Haugh; III: Assembly on the Dimensions of Hunger and Malnutrition; IV: Miscellaneous; and V: Interview Tapes.
Series I: Study of the Public Voluntary Not for Profit Sector of Colonial City: This series is divided into four sub-series: A: The Dissertation; B: The Interviews; C: Resources; and D: Proposals, Drafts, and Notes.
Sub-series A: The Dissertation: This sub-series contains chapters 1-6 of the dissertation. These appear to be drafts, and not the final copies. Chapter 1 states the problem to be studied. Chapter 2 reviews the relevant literature. Chapter 3 discusses the methods used in the study. It also gives a personal background on James Haugh to help readers understand his interests, background, motivations, and biases in the study. Chapter 4 discusses what it is to be a Virginian. Chapter 5 explains the arrangements of power and influence in Colonial City. Chapter 6 profiles the influential people of Colonial City. These people are referred to as 'deans' and 'godfathers'. Also, included in this sub-series is the transcript from a class talk about James Haugh's book, Power and Influence in a Colonial City, which is the final copy of his dissertation. In this talk, he reveals that Colonial City is actually Norfolk, Virginia.
Sub-series B: The Interviews: This sub-series contains transcripts of James Haugh's interviews with nearly sixty of Norfolk's most prominent citizens in 1977-78. Also included are biographies, newspaper clippings, notes, and other material associated with these people.
Sub-series C: Resources: This sub-series contains resource material related to this study. Included are journal articles, pamphlets, newspaper clippings, membership lists, and information on the Junior League of Norfolk - Virginia Beach.
Sub-series D: Proposals, Drafts, and Notes: This sub-series contains drafts of James Haugh's dissertation proposals; rough drafts and final copies of a few of the chapters of the dissertation; appendices, charts, and other information from the study; and notes related to the study.
Series II: Other Paper and Course Work by Haugh: This series contains other papers written by James Haugh for his classes. Most of his papers related to power, influence, and social change. This series also includes notes, bibliographies, and exam materials.
Series III: Assembly on the Dimensions of Hunger: This series contains a transcripts from meetings their June 11, 1975 Awareness meeting and first annual meeting, minutes of their May 2, 1977 meeting, and a program from their March 1978 conference.
Series IV: Miscellaneous: This series contains paperwork related to James Haugh's 1978 graduation from the University of Akron, a sketch of floor plans for a house, a guide to the architectural styles in Norfolk, Virginia, a listing of funny laws, and an article about Anita Bryant's crusade against homosexuals.
Series V: Interview tapes: This series contains 48 audiocassettes of Jim Haugh's interviews with Norfolk's most prominent citizens in 1978.
Contents List
- Study of the Public Voluntary Not for Profit Sector of Colonial City
  - The Dissertation
    - Chapter 1 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Chapter 2 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Chapter 3 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Chapter 4 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Chapter 5 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Chapter 6 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Power and Influence in Colonial City (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 7)
  - The Interviews
    - Connie Laws (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Jean Bruce (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Harry B. Price, Jr. (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Joshua P. Darden (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Charles L. Kaufman (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 12)
    - J. Pretlow Darden (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Richard F. Welton III (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Harry B. Price III (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 15)
    - W. Wright Harrison, Virginia National Bank (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Thomas McNamara (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 17)
    - James L. Bugg (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Harvey Lindsey, Jr. (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 19)
    - G. William Whitehurst (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 20)
    - The Honorable William B. Spong, Jr. (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Toy Savage (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 2)
    - General Robert C. Hixon (I) (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 3)
    - General Robert C. Hixon (II) (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 4)
    - W. Mackenzie Jenkins, Jr. (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Harry Mansbach (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 6)
    - John L. Roper (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Charles Burroughs (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Alf Mapp (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Mr. Robert L. Fodrey (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Mrs. Harrison B. Wilson (Lucy) (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Mrs. Justine Nusbaum (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Mrs. Mason (Sabine) Andrews (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Mr. Harvey Johnson, Jr. (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Eleanor Bradshaw (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Henry Clay Hofheimer, II (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Mr. Garett Epps, Jr. (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Preston Blake (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Colgate W. Darden, Jr. (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Mrs. Alvin Margolious (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Frank A. Batten, III (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Mason Andrews, M.D. Vice Mayor of Norfolk (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 4)
    - M. Lee Payne, President: United Virginia Bank (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Mrs. Lee Anne Avery (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Eugene Berris (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Ralph Cousins, Adm. (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Charles M. Reynolds (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Mrs. Emily (George) Harkins (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Harrison B. Wilson (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Heath Light (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Richard E. Rumble (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 13)
    - C.B. White (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 14)
    - Helen Withers (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Charles O. Burgess (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 16)
    - Robert Lawrence, Associate Director Health Welfare, Recreation Planning Council (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 17)
    - Herbert Fisher, Pastor, Ivy Farms Church of the Brethren Chairman Steering Committee (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 18)
    - Vince Thomas (Box-folder Box 4, Folder 1)
    - George Rice, Director, The Planning Council (Box-folder Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Dorothy Frame (Box-folder Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Donald Hugh Smith (Box-folder Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Dale Lick, Dean, School of Sciences & Health Professions: Old Dominion University (Box-folder Box 4, Folder 5)
    - George C. Crawley (Box-folder Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Jean DeVita, Staff, Assembly in the Dimensions of Hunger/Malnutrition (Box-folder Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Margery Loomis Krome (Box-folder Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Resources
    - Theory Summary (Box-folder Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Papers of Bell and Calina (Box-folder Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Terry Clark-Community Decision Making (Box-folder Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Emerson, Richard M., Power-Dependence Relations 1962 ASR (Box-folder Box 4, Folder 12)
    - Sennett: Fascination of Sacrifice (Box-folder Box 4, Folder 13)
    - Wilensky: Structural Assimilation (Box-folder Box 4, Folder 14)
    - Wilensky: The Professionalization of Everyone? (Box-folder Box 4, Folder 15)
    - Wilensky: Mass Society and Mass Culture Interdependence and Independence (Box-folder Box 4, Folder 16)
    - Journal Articles (Box-folder Box 4, Folder 17)
    - Planning Council (Box-folder Box 4, Folder 18)
    - Miscellaneous Articles & Pamphlets (Box-folder Box 4, Folder 19)
    - Newspaper Clippings (Box-folder Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Junior League (Box-folder Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Annual Report of the Junior League of Norfolk-Virginia Beach (Box-folder Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Proposals, Drafts, and Notes
    - Research Ideas (Box-folder Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Notes (Box-folder Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Impressions (Box-folder Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Gail Austin (Box-folder Box 5, Folder 7)
    - George Kregger-for Jim Haugh (Box-folder Box 5, Folder 8)
    - Copies (Box-folder Box 5, Folder 9)
    - Deutscher Paper Notes (Box-folder Box 5, Folder 10)
    - Dissertation Proposal (Box-folder Box 5, Folder 11)
    - Proposal (Box-folder Box 5, Folder 12)
    - Notes for Proposal, June 19, 1978 (Box-folder Box 5, Folder 13)
    - Notes for Proposal, June 21, 1978 (Box-folder Box 5, Folder 14)
    - Outline Proposal (Box-folder Box 5, Folder 15)
- Other Papers and Course Work by Haugh
  - Final Community Project for O'Brien, J. Haugh (Box-folder Box 6, Folder 1)
  - First Draft of Basis of Power (Box-folder Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Amos Hawley, etc. (Box-folder Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Proposal-Deutscher, August 18, 1977 (Box-folder Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Private Trouble to Public Issue: An Exercise in Evaluating Social Change (Box-folder Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Untitled I (Box-folder Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Untitled II (Box-folder Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Compulsory Exam (Box-folder Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Community Organization Comprehensive Exam, May 15-16, 1978; July 18 1978; January 6 1978 (Box-folder Box 6, Folder 9)
- Assembly on the Dimensions of Hunger and Malnutrition
  - Awareness Meeting, June 11, 1975 (Box-folder Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Assembly Against Hunger (and) Malnutrition-Minutes, May 2, 1977 (Box-folder Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Program/Conference, March 22-23, 1978 (Box-folder Box 6, Folder 12)
  - First Annual Meeting (Box-folder Box 6, Folder 13)
- Miscellaneous
  - University of Akron-Fall Graduation (Box-folder Box 6, Folder 14)
  - House Floor Plans (Box-folder Box 6, Folder 15)
  - An Illustrated Guide to the Major Architectural Styles in Norfolk, Virginia (Box-folder Box 6, Folder 16)
  - Funny Laws (Box-folder Box 6, Folder 17)
  - Homosexuality (Box-folder Box 6, Folder 18)
- Interview Tapes
  - 24 audiocassette tapes of interviews in the Colonial City Study (Box Box 7)
  - 24 audiocassette tapes of interviews in the Colonial City Study (Box Box 8)